Guide to the Kohut Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kohut family papers
1880-1966
1890-1935
MS 956
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(4 boxes)
The family of Abraham and Rebekah Bettelheim Kohut were prominent in the New York Jewish community, and involved in relgious affairs and education. The Kohut School for Girls was operated in New York City from 1899-1905 by Rebekah Kohut. The papers consist primarily of Kohut family memorabilia, photographs, correspondence, and other material. Also included are two ledgers from the Kohut School for Girls for academic year 1904-1905 listing students' names with charges for tuition, books, and other details.
Kohut family
General note
The collection was formerly known as the Kohut Girl's School Records (MS 956). With subsequent additions, Kohut family material now predominates and the title of the collection was changed to reflect this in 2009.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the stacks of Sterling Memorial Library, 1942; transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator, 2001, 2007, and 2009.
Custodial History
Materials in this collection were received at various times from the Kohut family and descendants of Gisela Kahn Gresser, a granddaughter of Alexander Kohut, by the Yale University Library and the Judaica Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The family of Abraham and Rebekah Bettelheim Kohut were prominent in the New York Jewish community, and involved in relgious affairs and education. The Kohut School for Girls was operated in New York City from 1899-1905 by Rebekah Kohut. The papers consist primarily of Kohut family memorabilia, photographs, correspondence, and other material. Also included are two ledgers from the Kohut School for Girls for academic year 1904-1905 listing students' names with charges for tuition, books, and other details. The Kohut family endowed the Alexander Kohut Memorial Fund for the purchase of Judaica materials by the Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander Kohut was born in Hungary on April 22, 1842. He completed rabbinical studies in Breslau and received a Ph.D. from the University of Leipzig. In 1885 he came to the United States to serve as the chief rabbi of Congregation Ahavath Chesed in New York City. Kohut died on May 25, 1894, in New York City. Rebekah Bettelheim Kohut was born in Hungary on September 9, 1864, and immigrated to the United States with her family in 1864. She married Alexander Kohut in 1887, and raised his eight children from a previous marriage. Following his death, she founded and ran the Kohut School for Girls in New York City from 1899-1905. She was a prominent figure in helping to organize Jewish women's groups in New York, and in 1923 became president of the World Congress for Jewish Women. She died in New York City on August 11, 1951. George A. Kohut (1874-1933) was a son of Alexander Kohut, a scholar, and a librarian at the Jewish Theological Seminary of America.
Education; Jews -- United States; Women -- Education; Women; New York (N.Y.); Account books; Letters; Photographs; Kohut, Alexander, 1842-1894; Kohut, George Alexander, 1874-1933; Kohut, Rebekah Bettelheim, 1864-1951; Kohut School for Girls
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  Includes Accession 2002-M-046.
  - Ledgers from the Kohut School for Girls, Circa 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Family papers
    - Epitaph of Israel Kohut and Columbia Teachers College registration booklet of Elsie Kohut, Circa 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Epitaph is in Hebrew and is undated.
    - Photographs of Kohut family members and copy of a bookplate for the Alexander Kohut Memorial Collection, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional material, Circa 1880-1966; Accession 2007-M-043
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Includes materials transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator in 2007 and 2009.
  - Correspondence, Circa 1886-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, certificates, vita, and other materials, 1892-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Citation for Rebekah Kohut, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorials for Rev. Dr. Alexander Kohut, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Papers concerning the estate of George A. Kohut, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Circa 1880-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    Primarily portrait photographs of various members of the Kohut and Gresser families.
    - Photograph of unidentified man and charcoal sketch of unidentified woman, Circa 1880-1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Likely members of the extended Kohut family.
    - Oversize photographs, Circa 1880-1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Printed ephemera and Kohut biographical material, 1894-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printed manuscript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Possibly in Turkish or Persian.
  - Scrapbook of Alexander Kohut, Circa 1883-1910 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Contains primarily clippings and printed ephemera in German, Hebrew, English, and other languages, and also includes some photographs of Alexander Kohut.
    - Loose material removed from scrapbook, Circa 1883-1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings, Circa 1900-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)